Guide to the Allan R. Holmberg collection on Peru, circa 1946-1966.
Holmberg, Allan R., collection on Peru, circa 1946-1966
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Allan R. Holmberg collection on Peru, circa 1946-1966.
14-25-1529
Holmberg, Allan R.
46 cubic feet
Correspondence, reports, publications, photographs.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
The materials in this collection reflect the research of Allan R. Holmberg and others in Peru, most notably relating to the Cornell Peru Project but also including materials on the Cornell Cross-Cultural Methodology Project and Holmberg's research in Viru, Peru.
ORGANIZATIONAL HISTORY
The aim of the Cornell Peru Project was to conduct an experiment in applied anthropology dealing with social and cultural change among the Indian serfs of the Andean hacienda (an agricultural manor) of Vicos, located in the Callejon de Huaylas of Peru. It also was to give training to social scientists in applied field work in anthropology. The Peruvian Indian Institute, a semi-autonomous agency attached to the Ministry of Labor and Indian Affairs, collaborated in this project. Cornell University, under Professor Holmberg's direction, leased the Vicos hacienda for a five year period. During that five year period from 1951-1956, the Vicos community changed from one of serfdom under the rule of a "patron," to that of an autonomous, self-governing and economically viable community. After the five year period, Cornell continued as advisor to the Vicos community and to the Peruvian Ministry of Labor and Indian Affairs until 1965. Another division of the collection, the Cross-Cultural Methodology Project, was composed of the records of a group of social scientists at Cornell University who obtained funds from the Carnegie Foundation of New York to carry out a comparative study of social science methods in different areas of the world. A Peruvian phase of this study was carried out by Professor Rose Goldsen at Vicos, Peru in 1952-1953. Dr. Max Ralis was involved with this study in Thailand and India.
Chronological List of Funding and Personnel for Projects Included in the Vicos Collection*
1947 Carnegie Corporation of New York five-year grant for establishment of the Cornell University Studies in Culture and Applied Science (CUSCAS) program. Included teaching and research on cultural change in the American Southwest, India, Latin America, and Thailand.
1949 Preliminary study of Hacienda Vicos by Mario C. Vazquez.
1951 Carnegie Corporation of New York grant to Cornell University for continuation of CUSCAS, including five-year experiment in culture change at Vicos. Contributions also came from Wenner-Gren Foundation for Anthropological Research and the Social Science Research Council. Allan R. Holmberg, Director of the Cornell Peru Project, and Carlos Monge M., Director of the Instituto Indigenista Peruana, arranged for the cooperation of the two institutions.
1952 Finalization of the rental of Hacienda Vicos from the Sociedad de Beneficencia Publica de Huaraz. Patronship was jointly held by the Cornell Peru Project and the Instituto Indigenista Peruana, with Holmberg and Monge as co-directors. Holmberg acted as the first Field Director of the Vicos experimental station.
1952-1953 William Mangin acted as Field Director of the Vicos experimental station.
1953 Cornell Methodology Project in Vicos, funded by a Rockefeller Foundation grant. Directed by Rose K. Goldsen, with assistance from Bryce Ryan and Richard Patch.
1953-1956 William Blanchard acted as Field Director of the Vicos experimental station.
1954 May Kedney did a private study of the use of visual arts in education in the Vicos school.
1954-1955 Cornell Methodology Project in Bang Chan, Thailand, funded by a Rockefeller Foundation grant. Directed by Max Ralis and Robert Textor.
1956 Dr. Marshall T. Newman of the Division of Physical Anthropology, Smithsonian Institution, conducted growth and maturation studies with Vicos school children. Dr. Fred Allen of the Blood Grouping Laboratory of Boston, Mass., did blood groups studies.
1957-1962 Mario C. Vazquez acted as Field Director of the Vicos experimental station.
1959-1962 Henry F. Dobyns acted as Research Coordinator of the Cornell Peru Project.
1959-1964 Carnegie Corporation of New York grant for Cornell Peru Project.
1960-1965 Columbia-Cornell-Harvard-Illinois Summer Field Study Program.
1962 Transfer of community title to the Vicosinos finalized. Cost of the sale was 3,256,861 soles, 2 million of which was paid directly by the community. U.S. Peace Corps contract with Cornell University for the training of Peru III volunteers. Directed by Paul L. Doughty.
1962-1964 Paul L. Doughty acted as Research Coordinator of the Cornell Peru Project.
1963-1966 Comparative Studies of Cultural Change program, funded by a contract with the U.S. Agency for International Development (contract AID/csd-296). Included with the Cornell India and Thailand Projects, the Cornell Peru Project with Allan R. Holmberg as Director and Henry F. Dobyns as Associate Director of the Project and Coordinator of the Program. With the death of Holmberg in 1966, Dobyns became Director of the Cornell Peru Project, 1966-1967.
1964 Mario C. Vazquez acted as Research Coordinator of the Cornell Peru Project. Andean Indian Community Research and Development program, funded by a contract with the U.S. Agency for International Development (contract AID/ia-206). Colquiri, study of nationalized mines in Bolivia, requested by COMIBOL, the state mining corporation.
*Individual studies by graduate students or others supervised wholly or in part by Cornell staff are omitted from this listing but can be found in Cornell Peru Project bibliographies.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
The subject matter of the materials from the Cornell Peru Project consists of working operations in Vicos. The types of material include correspondence; census forms; census returns; a land tenure survey; hydrological data; Vicos hacienda purchase agreement; accounts and account books; interviews with the Vicosinos; Human Relations Area Files (HRAF) field notes on Vicos and also the communities of Viru, Marcara, Recuayhuanca, Paucartambo, and Huaylas; monographs, reprints, publications, and unpublished articles; 3x5 bibliographic cards; code sheets; field notebooks; field note stencils; field notes; HRAF interview data; interview guides; interview sheets; life histories; maps; questionnaires; photographs; slides; and other miscellaneous materials. Also included are films of miscellaneous footage of Vicos and inhabitants taken by C.P.P. staff. Material relating to Allan Holmberg's work in Viru, Peru consists of correspondence and subject files. The material relating to the Cornell Cross-Cultural Methodology Project consists of interviews with Vicosinos, lists of respondents, and notebooks with cross-cultural methodology material (including Vicos material).
SUBJECTS
Names:
Dobyns, Henry F.; Goldsen, Rose Kohn.; Holmberg, Allan R.; Vazquez, Mario C.; Cornell Peru Project.; Cornell University. Dept. of Anthropology.; Human Relations Area Files, inc.; Instituto Indigenista Peruano.
Subjects:
Applied anthropology--Peru--Vicos.; Anthropology--Research.; Anthropology--Methodology.; Cross cultural studies.; Social change.
Places:
Vicos (Peru).; Viru (Peru).; Marcara (Peru).; Recuayhuanca (Peru).; Paucartambo (Peru).; Huaylas (Peru).; Lima (Peru).; Peru.; Andes.
Form and Genre Terms:
Field notes.; Maps.; Questionnaires.; Photographs.; Slides (photographs).
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Available Copies:
Numerous photographs and documents from the collection have been digitized and are accessible via the Web at: http://www.library.cornell.edu/spr47/vicos/index.html.
RELATED MATERIALS
Henry F. Dobyns papers, 1960s. #6803.
Paul L. Doughty collection of Vicos photographs, 1960-1969. #6734.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Cornell Peru Project (Accession 1)
Administrative Materials
Administrative Papers and General Information
Individual Reports and Projects, and Correspondence
Analytical Models and Techniques
Administrative Correspondence
Financial Accounts and Labor Records
Field Data
Field Notebooks
Environmental and Land Tenure Data
HRAF Files and Other Field Notes
Censuses and Surveys
Health Clinic Records
Reprints, Publications and Papers
Microfilms, Audiotapes and Motion Picture Films
Visual Materials
Series II. Cornell Peru Project (Accession 2)
Series III. Viru
Series IV. Cornell Methodology Project
Administration and Operation in Vicos, Ancash, Peru
Field Data from Vicos, Ancash, Peru
Series V. Miscellaneous Files
Separated Materials
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Cornell Peru Project (Accession 1)
  This material comprises part of the original collection represented by the published guide compiled by Deborah Wood in 1975. Series IV. Cornell Methodology Project is the other part of the original collection.
  - Administrative Materials
    This subseries includes many types of material resulting from administration of the Vicos field station and the activities of various projects done under the auspices of the CPP (Cornell Peru Project). The three major types of material are distinguished by the three sub-subseries.
    - Administrative Papers and General Information
      This section consists of administrative papers and general information. Important types of material are notes, reports, correspondence, and questionnaires. Activities and administrative considerations throughout the time of Cornell's involvement in Vicos are documented; items include Cornell Peru Project proposals and progress reports, and a copy of the Vicos purchase agreement. This section is arranged in three subject groups: first, administrative reports and general information; second, individual reports and projects, and correspondence; and third, analytical models and techniques.
      - a. Vicos Purchase Agreement b. hacienda ownership - transfer to community e. Cornell Peru Project, Ministerio de Trabajo y Asuntos Indigenas, Sociedad de Beneficencia Publica de Huaraz f. legal document g. Vicos, Ancash, Peru, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - a. Holmberg Proposal '55 and 1st Progress Report b. proposal-behavioral science research and development project, improvements--hacienda Vicos c. Holmberg, Allan R. f. reports g. Vicos, Ancash, Peru, 1952-1955 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - a. Cornell Peru Project Report 1963-1964 b. improvements-hacienda Vicos, Peace Corps project activities, U.S. enterprise in Latin America-problems e. Cornell Peru Project, Plan Nacional de Integracion de la Poblacion Aborigen, Peace Corps f. report, article g. Latin America; Vicos, Ancash, Peru, 1957-1964 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - a. Comparative Studies of Cultural Change b. proposal-institutional change and economic growth, research proposal-technological change research-Vicos, budget-five year study c. Morse, Chandler; Wolf, Charles Jr. e. Carnegie Corp. f. reports g. Cornell University, NY, USA, 1951-1954 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - a. Administration Dept. of Anthropology b. mailing list, personnel, department files, policy, custodial duties-collections, Peru-Cornell relations, inventory of Peru project materials, project termination c. Roberts, John M.; Lynch, Thomas F.; Vazquez, Mario C.; Dobyns, Henry F. e. Cornell University Dept. of Anthropology, Cornell Peru Project f. correspondence, lists, memoranda, report g. Cornell University, NY, USA, 1964-1966 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Report on Vicos Project and Cornell, from Mario Vazquez, January 31, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - a. Peru: Laws 1820-1961 Indian Affairs/Land b. agrarian indigenists laws f. lists g. Peru, 1820-1962 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - a. Vicos Publicity '53-'57 b. improvements-hacienda Vicos, nutrition studies, hacienda ownership-transfer to community f. articles, clippings g. Peru; Vicos, Ancash, Peru, 1953-1957 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - a. Vicos Background Publications b. liberal education, ethnological investigation f. pamphlets g. Puerto Rico; Lima, Peru, 1953; Bibliography: Matos Mar, Jose, et al., Investigaciones Etnologicas en Huarochiri (Peru), 1953 Valcarcel, Luis E., El Conocimiento Cientifico de los Pueblos del Peru, 1953 Villaronga, Mariano, La Educacion Liberal, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Individual Reports and Projects, and Correspondence
        - a. Vicos: Teaching Unit Elementary School b. Social Studies resource unit, Incas, hacienda system e. Newton Schools Foundation, Inc. f. photographs, outlines g. West Newton, Massachusetts, USA, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 10-13)
        - a. Marcara Data H. Ghersi Barrera b. dramas--"Los Autos Sacramentales" and "El Sacrificio de Mariz Parado de Bellido," layout sketches of Marcara locale, local govt. problems, Dept. of Ancash--source bibliography, mine disaster--Quebrado, Honda, flood 1949, Ancash description, record fragments-Hacienda Vicos 1900-1915 c. Vellard, Jean e. Universidad Mayor de San Marcos f. scripts, maps, correspondence, sketch, list, photos, post cards, negatives, clippings, broadsides, 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 14)
        - a. Biography of Herminio Colonia b. life history c. Colonia, Herminio; Vazquez, Mario C. f. report, 1954-1958 (Box 1, Folder 15)
        - a. Hilario Gonzalez b. life history c. Gonzalez, Hilario; Stein, William W. f. manuscript g. Vicos, Ancash, Peru, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 16)
        - a. Viru-Peasants MS, Vazquez b. land tenure, agricultural practices, rural population c. Vazquez, Mario C. f. report g. Viru, Peru, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 17)
        - a. Vicos Peruvian Student Reports [consists of list of original folder contents] (Box 1, Folder 18)
        - a. Cornell Peru Project Reports b. Vicos project activities, photographic essay, field-worker instructions for tareas, New Seed Potatoes introduction, cross-cultural methodology study design, participant intervention justification, research and development studies, school children artwork, economic development studies--Santa Corp., culture change studies--Hualcan e. Cornell Methodology Project, Cornell Peru Project, Corp. Peruana del Santa f. reports, articles, periodical, list g. Vicos, Ancash, Peru; Peru; Hualcan, Ancash, Peru, 1952-1959 (Box 1, Folder 19)
          Blanchard, William C., Anthropological Study and Experiment at Hacienda Vicos, 1954
          Collier, John Jr., Vicos A Story of Anthropology: A Photographic Account of Social Science Helping a Backward People, n.d.
          Goldsen, Rose K., Instructions Given to Fieldworkers, 1953
          ---, Matchinq of Items in Vicos Questionnaire with Concepts They are Designed to Measure, n.d.
          ---, The Introduction of NSP in Vicos: The Story Line, 1955
          Holmberg, Allan R., Experimental Intervention in a Field Situation, 1955
          ---, "Participant Intervention in the Field" Human Organization 14:1, 1955
          ---, Some Experiments in Socioeconomic Change in an Underdeveloped Area, n.d.
          ---, "Land Tenure and Planned Social Change: A Case from Vicos, Peru," Human Organization 18:1, 1959
          Kedney, May, A Report of work with Thirteen Children in the Hacienda Vicos School, 1954
          Montalvo, Abner, Salud Publica y una Pelicula en Vicos, 1955
          Patch, Richard, Comparative Economic Systems of Non-Western People, 1953
          ---, Corporation Peruana del Santa and the Economic Development of Peru, 1953
          Seed Potato Tarea Variables, n.d.
          Stein, William W., Cultural Stability and Change in Hualcan, and Andean Indian Estancia, 1952
          List of missing items.
        - a. Student Reports, Summer Field Study b. field studies--locations--topics e. Columbia-Cornell-Harvard-Illinois Summer Field Study Program f. lists g. Columbia University, NY, USA, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 20)
        - a. Viru-1965-Prelims, Anthropology 412, Summer Field Program b. student project proposals c. Brewer, Sharon; Bengelsdorf, Carol L.; Bourque, Susie; Gilbert, Gordon; Hahn, Robert; Hollerbach, Paula E.; Richardson, Gail; Taylor e. Cornell University Dept. of Anthropology f. reports, bibliography, correspondence g. Viru, Peru (Box 1, Folder 21)
        - a. Permission to Publish b. publication approval c. Dobyns, Henry F. e. Contract No. AID/csd-292, Comparative Studies of Cultural Change f. correspondence, 1964-1966 (Box 1, Folder 22)
        - a. Comparative Studies of Cultural Change--AID b. Bolivia studies, reports distribution publication approval, progress report AID c. Dobyns, Henry F.; Holmberg, Allan R.; Turner, Frank L. e. Comparative Studies of Cultural Change, Contract No. AID/csd-296 f. correspondence, memoranda, report, 1962-1965 (Box 1, Folder 23)
        - a. Holmberg-Vazquez Holmberg-Murdock b. guerilla activities, Peru-Cornell cooperation, publication approval c. Guevara, Che; Vazquez, Mario C.; Murdock, George P.; Holmberg, Allan R. e. Inst. of Inter-American Affairs, Public Health Division f. correspondence g. Lima, Peru, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 24)
        - a. Technicon b. storage facilities e. Cornell University Department of Anthropology f. pamphlets, correspondence, inventory, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - Analytical Models and Techniques
        - a. Marcara Household Census Questionnaire and Code b. Household Census variables, Household census coding design f. lists g. Marcara, Ancash, Peru (Box 1, Folder 26)
        - a. Vicos Questionnaires b. data gathering c. Patch, Richard W. f. questionnaires g. Vicos, Ancash, Peru; Callejon de Huaylas, Ancash, Peru, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 27)
        - a. Recuayhuanca Questionnaires b. interview for district officials c. Snyder, Joan f. questionnaire g. Recuayhuanca, Ancash, Peru (Box 1, Folder 28)
        - a. Vicos Questionnaires b. interviewer suggestions, data gathering c. Snyder, Joan; Patch, Richard W. f. questionnaires, list g. Recuayhuanca, Ancash, Peru; Vicos, Ancash, Peru; Hualcan, Ancash, Peru (Box 1, Folder 29)
        - a. Vicos Analytical Models b. Input-output analysis system c. Hopper, W. David f. reports g. Vicos, Ancash, Peru (Box 1, Folder 30)
        - a. Vicos: New Seed Potato Analysis Sheets b. introduction of New Seed Potato, New Seed Potato use analysis f. report, questionnaires g. Vicos, Ancash, Peru, 1952-1954 (Box 1, Folder 31-37)
    - Administrative Correspondence
      The administrative correspondence is mostly from 1953-1956 while William C. Blanchard was field director in Vicos. The inclusive dates are 1951-1956. There are two sections in this part: one, correspondence between the CPP and the IPP (Instituto Indigenista Peruana); and two, between the Vicos field station and outside individuals or organizations. The correspondence came to the archives arranged in this manner; it had been maintained as a file by Maxine and William Blanchard while they were in Vicos. In the first section activities and problems arising from joint administration of Hacienda Vicos by CPP and IIP are central topics. This section is arranged chronologically. The chief correspondents are William C. Blanchard, Carlos Monge M., Director of IIP, and Manuel D. Velasco Nunez, Secretary General of IIP. In the second section, the correspondence relates to the organization and maintenance of hacienda operations or to arrangements for studies to be conducted at Vicos. The financial accounts of CPP with various banks are included in this section. The arrangement is alphabetical by sender.
      - Correspondence Between Cornell Peru Project and Instituto Indigenista Peruano
        - a. Instituto Indigenista Peruano--Cornell Peru Project Correspondence b. project activities authorization, project supplies acquisition, Vicos school arrangements, Chancos maintenance, medical survey, administrative transactions c. Mangin, William; Monge Medrano, Carlos; Velasco Nunez, Manuel D.; Blanchard, William C.; Holmberg, Allan R. e. Instituto Indigenista Peruano, Cornell Peru Project, Universidad Nacional Mayor de San Marcos de Lima f. correspondence, receipts, telegrams g. Vicos, Ancash, Peru; Lima, Peru, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 1)
        - a. Instituto Indigenista Peruano--Cornell Peru Project Correspondence b. organizing project studies, medical survey, Vicos school arrangements, progress reports, adult education, project supplies acquisition, agricultural program, administrative transactions, public health studies, future jurisdiction of Vicos, acculturation--radio presentation c. Blanchard, William C.; Monge M., Carlos; Velasco Nunez, Manuel D.; Gil Quevedo, Ciro; Collier, John Jr. e. Instituto Indigenista Peruano; Cornell Peru Project; Proyecto Proqramo Pativilca-Huarez-Huaylas del Ministerio de Salud; Compania Administradora del Guano f. correspondence, telegrams, reports, receipts g. Vicos, Ancash, Peru; Lima, Peru, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 2)
        - a. Instituto Indigenista Peruano--Cornell Peru Project Correspondence b. project activities authorization, progress reports, photographic essay, project supplies acquisition, administrative transactions, Vicos school arrangements, acculturation of Peruvian indigenous population c. Velasco Nunez, Manuel D.; Gil Quevedo, Ciro; Monge M., Carlos; Blanchard, William C.; Collier, John Jr. e. Instituto Indigenista Peruano, Cornell Peru Project, UNICEF, Compania Administradora del Guano f. correspondence, receipts, reports, telegrams g. Vicos, Ancash, Peru; Lima, Peru, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 3)
        - a. Instituto Indigenista Peruano--Cornell Peru Project Correspondence b. administrative transactions, Vicos school arrangements, project supplies acquisition, progress reports, anthropometric study arrangements, products and work of rural schools--exposition, project reorganization c. Blanchard, William C.; Velasco Nunez, Manuel D.; Monge M., Carlos; Newman, Marshall T.; Gil Quevado, Ciro; Allen, Fred H. Jr.; Holmberg, Allan R. e. Instituto Indigenista Peruano, Cornell Peru Project, Smithsonian Institution f. correspondence, telegrams, reports, receipts, inventory g. Vicos, Ancash, Peru; Lima, Peru, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Correspondence Between Vicos Field Station and Outside Individuals or Organizations
        - a. A b. blood grouping study, shipping arrangements, hacienda construction, indigenous education c. Alers-Montalvo, Manuel; Blanchard, William C.; Allen, Fred H. Jr.; Almandos Garcia, Aliro; Anselmi, M. S. e. Instituto Interamericano de Ciencias Agrícolas, The Blood Grouping Laboratory, Cornell Peru Project, Alltransport S.A. f. correspondence, telegram, receipts, report g. Vicos, Ancash, Peru; Lima, Peru; Boston, Mass., USA, 1953-1956 (Box 2, Folder 5)
        - a. B b. project financial account, duplication of Methodology project notes, hacienda lease c. Blanchard, William C.; Barnett, Clifford; Basto Giron, Luis J.; Solís Carrion, Jose e. Banco de Credito del Peru, Sociedad Publica de Beneficencia de Huaraz, Cornell Peru Project f. correspondence, lists, receipts, bank statements g. Vicos, Ancash, Peru; Lima, Peru; Huaraz, Ancash, Peru, 1953-1956 (Box 2, Folder 6)
        - a. C, E, F b. information requests, tax status--non-resident citizens, photographic study, film documentary, services rendered to project, authorization of project personnel, visitors to Vicos c. Blanchard, William C.; Caso, Alfonso; Collier, John Jr. e. Instituto Nacional Indigenista; Instituto Indigenista Interamericano; Concejo Provincial de Carhuaz; The Rockefeller Foundation, Cornell Peru Project f. correspondence, telegrams g. Vicos, Ancash, Peru; Mexico, F., Mexico; Carhuaz, Ancash, Peru; New York, NY, USA, 1953-1956 (Box 2, Folder 7)